Speaking about the history of UNIX and Linux
we can recall the well-known saying -
we make our inventions stand on the shoulders
of giants
But we must understand
That many of those giants have failed
but such fails can be a good lesson
for new developers.
One of such giant was a MULTICS project.
The development of MULTICS began in
1965 as a research project
by MIT, General Electric and
Bell Labs to create a time sharing,
multi-processing and multi-user interactive
operating system.
After several years of development the enthusiasm
of the developers decreased more and more
as the system became more and more complex
and the prospects for completion of development
became less and less.
Bell Labs pulled out of the project 1969;
but some of the people who worked on it got
a lot of experience
Among them were Ken Thompson and Dennis Ritchie
of Bell Labs,
the inventors of the UNIX operating system
It's funny,
but the history of Unix systems is closely
related to computer games
It started in 1969
When Ken Thompson discovered an old PDP7 computer
in a dark corner of the lab
and wanted to use it to play Space Travel
game.
There was little to do --
an operating system had to be written to run
it.
And he did it --
at midnight on January 1st, 1970,
the Unix epoch began.
From this time on,
all clocks in UNIX-like system
count down that time,
including your mobile phone.
Originally It was a single tasking operating
system
written in assembly language
that was loaded from paper tapes and
called UNICS as opposed to the complexity
of MULTICS.
And then the team of Ken Thompson and Dennis
Ritchie
received a new Digital Equipment Corporation
PDP11 computer
to develop a word processing system for the
Bell Labs patent department.
For the first three months
the machine sat in a corner,
enumerating all the closed Knight's tours
on a 6×8 chess board --
just became the hard drive wasn't shipped
with a super new computer.
This time
could be used to choose a programming language,
because it was a computer with a completely
new architecture
and programs written on PDP7 assembler was
not useful for it.
And most interesting was the concept
of another project used in some research and
development projects including MULTICS -- BCPL.
It was a high-level programming language focused
on portability.
Most of this language was written in the language
itself,
and only a small machine dependent part was
written in assembly.
To support a new machine, only 1/5 of the
computer code
needed to be rewritten,
which usually took 2-5 man-months.
Thompson used the same concept
when writing his simplified successor to BCPL,
language B.
This language was
not very expressive and effective on the PDP11.
And in 1971
Ritchie started to improve B, which resulted
to created a new language C.
In 1973 the UNIX kernel was refactored on
C language
to follow the same concept of portability
--
most of the code was machine independent.
The system was distributed in source code
among
universities for a nominal fee, which served
as an explosive growth
on its popularity in 80s.
Almost all the developers of new computer
systems
Science this period have used UNIX as the
base platform for very new developments.
One of the
most famous of these
Is the Berkeley Software Distribution (BSD)
developed
at the University of California, Berkeley
based on Unix version 6 with
its own copyleft license.
And most of the hardware vendors of the 80s
used BSD as the base operating system for
their new computers.
Unix was not a significant part of at Bell
Laboratories business,
and it was not a problem for them.
But in the 1980s Bell Labs
split into several companies as a result of
an anti-trust law suite against AT&T.
The new UNIX System Laboratories company was
created and the new UNIX System 5
specification was developed.
Unix was that main business of this company,
and they were very aggressive in pushing the
new standard in the market.
And that has been the cause of Unix wars
against non-commercial developers including
BSD.
The commercialization
of Unix system market
and the move
to a closed development and
distribution model
has led to an
alternative movement --
the GNU.
What is GNU?
You know it's such an African animal.
But also it is a self-referential abbreviation
"GNU is Not Unix".
Richard Stallman founded the project in 1978
at MIT.
The GNU project is a mass collaborative initiative
for the development of free software.
The first goal of this project
was to develop a set of programs
similar to the standard set of utilities in
UNIX.
And in 1991
a Finnish student Linus Torvalds created his
own operating system kernel,
which is compatible with a UNIX operating
system,
called Linux
As he said later,
"Just for fun".
The Linux kernel, combined with the
set of utilities from the GNU project,
served as the basis for creating a complete
operating system, comparable in
capabilities to commercial UNIX systems, and
usually even
superior to them.